<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-18T01:50:17+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Harsh Gadodia</title><subtitle>Harsh Gadodia's Personal Website</subtitle><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Boxed Up By Requirements</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Boxed-Up-By-Requirements/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boxed Up By Requirements" /><published>2019-02-09T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-09T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Boxed-Up-By-Requirements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Boxed-Up-By-Requirements/">&lt;p&gt;In my second last semester in NUS as a computer engineering major, I decided to enrol in CS2102, database systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several things I was looking forward to while taking the class, but none more so than the opportunity to work in a group on a real project. CS2102 was notorious amongst computing students for having tough project requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to present the project to the teaching team at the end of the semester, especially having spent many sleepless nights working with my teammates on the project. While I was initially very excited to work on the project, working on it made me feel unsatisfied because I was not really free to be creative, I was at liberty of strict grading rubrics and concrete requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/databaseProject.png&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was offered an opportunity to intern for a year in California in my second semester of year 2. I simply couldn’t refuse. The timing couldn’t have been better; having completed three semesters in NUS and having taken most of my core requirements related to my core interests, software engineering. I thought being in an actual working environment couldn’t be more beneficial to my learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took up an offer to work at Epic! (www.getepic.com), a small start-up trying to revolutionise reading for kids between the ages of 5-12. They made reading for kids fun, and offered tens of thousands of books and other educational material virtually on iOS, Android, and computers through a beautiful, interactive experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being part of a start-up was challenging in many ways. For one, it requires you to wear many hats. A small company trying to make a big impact means that every employee is expected to work hard and move fast. Job scopes are often blurred to meet time lines. At the same time, I was fortunate to be part of a company that valued my time and respected my expectations to leave a better software engineer a year later; I was not made to do saikang (unpleasant and undesirable tasks) at all, and was treated like an equal. I was given liberty to choose the projects I wanted to part of based on my own interests, a true privilege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being part of a team making a consumer-facing product, and that too for kids, meant that perfecting user interface and user experience (UI/UX) was paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An immense amount of thought and planning went into designing even simple screens; let alone advanced features. One of my first tasks at Epic! was to engineer a quiz feature for kids. Having come from an academic background and this being my first internship, I was puzzled by the lack of concrete requirements, instead being guided by my own gut feel (along with lots of helpful guidance from senior engineers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end goal was to produce a feature (and by extension, an experience) that kids would love. That meant not just designing for kids, but also putting the child at the centre of the user experience. I was initially taken aback by how seriously this exercise was taken, especially because I was used to presenting my projects to teaching assistants and professors. This was different; my graders were the million children who used the product daily. This felt exhilarating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/epicScreenshots.png&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the two experiences of working for the database project and interning as dichotomous. Working on a school project, even if designed to mimic real-world requirements,  is fundamentally different from working in the real world.  Before interning at Epic!, I was not even aware of what the industry was looking for, and one-year at a start-up with top-notch technology standards really opened my eyes to the disconnect between academia and reality in the field of software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My database project, while designed for (mock) entrepreneurs and investors, was to be graded by university teaching staff. The same project was being pursued by a hundred other students; year after year. While my group and I tried to put users at the centre of the experience, we knew that it was the teaching team we had to please at the end of the day. It didn’t matter if we had the coolest designs or the most interactive work flow, our fate was to be decided by someone who had probably graded the same project year after year. We designed to catch his eye, and not to please the user. Furthermore, in the name of “fairness”, the project scope was extremely narrow - everyone had the same strict requirements, the same checkboxes they wanted ticked off. This is boring, stifles creativity, and is against the end goal of preparing students for the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was immensely different from my task at Epic!, where I was required to engineer a kick-ass experience for a million actual users. The database project required little creativity, one could even argue that being too creative would lead to a penalty for not meeting requirements. On the other hand, creativity was at the soul of the quiz feature at Epic!. 
The NUS vision, mission, and values are noble. They seem to at the very least, hint at preparing students for the workplace (thought the mission to educate, inspire and transform). However, along with these goals, NUS also shoulders the responsibility of fundamentally being an academic institution that is expected to fairly grade its students. There is a need to quantify the quality of its graduates in a fair yet competitive manner, lest its ranking in the world university surveys fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/nusVision.png&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The university takes an anamorphic view of class projects - while their end goal is to train for the workplace, the very act of coming up with and sticking to “fair” grading metrics means that little space is left for creativity. In my opinion, NUS, and most other universities in the world that follow a similar traditional grading scheme, should start to cut back on their grading rubrics, and instead allow students to apply knowledge in less restrictive way. Yes, that means that subjectivity is introduced into grades, but hey, who said the world out there is objective to begin with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic, but take the example of this very writing assignment; with the noble goal of asking students to reflect on two transformative learning experiences, but with a word limit of 1000 words. Definitely designed to ease grading and perhaps give students a better understanding of requirements, but perhaps penalising students who have more to say, or those who can say more with less. A box on creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, I hope to always take requirements with a bushel of salt. As a software engineering aspirant with entrepreneurial dreams, I constantly remind myself that Google, Facebook, Airbnb, Uber, Twitter, Grab, were not born out of requirements. As a matter of fact, many such disruptors practically danced at the line between legality and breaking the law when they first began. This does not however, mean that I completely disregard rules in place and project requirements - they have their place. But, to change the world (or at least scratch at the surface), I know I have to think much, much bigger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">In my second last semester in NUS as a computer engineering major, I decided to enrol in CS2102, database systems.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Something Borrowed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Something-Borrowed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Something Borrowed" /><published>2018-12-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-12-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Something-Borrowed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Something-Borrowed/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve always loved animals. It’s part of the reason that I’m vegetarian, and I’m fascinated by how they can co-exist with each other (and sometimes humans in the case of pets and farm animals) without the ability to talk to express complex ideas. Naturally, I was elated when a friend of my mom requested that we take care of her 4-year-old &lt;a href=&quot;https://dogtime.com/dog-breeds/maltipoo#/slide/1&quot;&gt;Maltipoo&lt;/a&gt;, Fluffy, for a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fluffy.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you already have a dog, much of what I have to say will have little to no added value to you)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having always wanted a dog and failing to have convinced my parents on multiple occasions to get our own, I was especially excited to have him home. These were some of my observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dogs are incredibly loving. Incredibly loyal, I have now experienced for myself how they have cemented their place as man’s best friend. I’ve never seen anyone happier (and I don’t think I ever will) than Fluffy was every time I returned home. I think this is because, to him, I have safely returned after leaving our territory. Furthermore, Fluffy would someone know if anyone from my family (and for a short 2 weeks, his) would be behind the door. Before we were even 5 feet away from the door, Fluffy would start barking to make sure someone would open the door as soon as possible. This is curious because I doubt our smell would make it past the door from a distance, and he wouldn’t be barking if it was the neighbours walking to the door adjacent to ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dogs ask for very little from you, but give you so much in return. Fluffy would only need to be walked a couple of times a day, and be given food. However, in return he would follow you around the house, making sure you are fine. He would somehow be able to sense if I was stressed, and would come and gently sit next to my feet, watching me and making sure I was okay. He would also be awake much before I would, but would be silently and patiently waiting for me to wake up at my bedside. He would greet me by climbing onto the bed and licking me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We loved taking care of Fluffy (or rather Fluffy taking care of us) so much that we picked him up again in a few weeks when his two of his owners were going overseas. He stayed with us for a week. It was painful to drop him back home today. Over the few weeks with us, I have also seen that Fluffy has begun to trust us more, now comfortable falling deep into sleep in our laps, and letting us carry him around the house without fearing that we might drop him (which was a big gear for him when we first got him).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bond that I have developed with Fluffy over a short three weeks is not commensurate to the length of time he has stayed with us. I can only imagine how strong a bond is between dogs and owners who live with each other for years, or over the dog’s lifetime. To a dog, you truly are his everything. I don’t think people who don’t have dogs will ever understand what it feels like to own one. Admittedly, I don’t too, but I definitely believe that life is insipid without a dog living with you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I’ve always loved animals. It’s part of the reason that I’m vegetarian, and I’m fascinated by how they can co-exist with each other (and sometimes humans in the case of pets and farm animals) without the ability to talk to express complex ideas. Naturally, I was elated when a friend of my mom requested that we take care of her 4-year-old Maltipoo, Fluffy, for a few weeks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Price We Pay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Price-We-Pay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Price We Pay" /><published>2018-12-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-12-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Price-We-Pay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Price-We-Pay/">&lt;p&gt;I was in a good mood today, heading to terminal 4 (Changi Airport Singapore) for a short vacation in Bali. The shuttle bus from terminal 3 was packed with equally excited travellers, most of which seemed to be Singaporean based on their looks and accents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bus arrived at the terminal, people (naturally) started to rush towards the exit to alight. No one wants to be last in a situation like this! However, it made me really sad that no one would give way to a family of three, one of whom was a small baby in a pram. The father, who alighted first, was carrying a light blue bag of baby supplies, and I assumed people would wait for the mother (who was right behind) to follow next with the baby in the pram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what happened instead is that people saw the mother with a pram as an opportunity to cut ahead of a slower passenger. The mother smiled in dismay, and I could see on her face that this was not the first time. I was a little shocked, but having grown up in Singapore, it was sadly not that surprising. (More on this below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wished that I had the courage to reprimand those people and say something. Perhaps I will the next time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singapore, a small city-state with people as its only natural resource, is fiercely competitive. We are, from young, taught that the most opportunities will be offered to those who perform the best. From streaming students based on their performances in specific to classes starting at just grade 2 (students in better classes are assigned the most senior teachers and given access to the best facilities like science labs), to testing all Singaporean students at grade 6 for admission into secondary schools into schools (the better schools have facilities like softball courts, rugby fields, and a full stadium with a running track while others may not even have a single grass field for students to play soccer on), Singaporeans are no strangers to a “meritocratic” society, where you are rewarded based on your performance and contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singapore has a pathological need to be efficient and fair in everything it does, and Singaporeans have been trained from young to fit into the larger puzzle that is the Singapore society without showing dissent. Those who go against the flow are punished by the government, or not taken seriously by society. The need to follow the rules is instilled in every Singaporean, but only at the cost of courtesy and sometimes, practicality. For example, my experience driving in Singapore has been that while most drivers are law-abiding, rarely would one be given way when changing lanes. Not only that, cars would intentionally speed up when they see someone trying to filter into their lane. I realised this was worse for new drivers, who had a probation plate on their car. Others would see this as an opportunity to bully, and would generally make matter worse for you by not giving you the space you need to change lanes. I actually removed my probation plate when I realised this was the case. Cars generally do not stop for pedestrians if there is no crosswalk, even if the person trying to cross the road is a mother with a young child or an old person. Many pedestrians are surprised when I give them way to cross the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the trains (called MRTs) in Singapore, every carriage has a few seats reserved for the needy - elderly, the handicapped, pregnant women, and the like. These seats are usually taken up by the deserving, and sometimes by others if no one is qualified enough to sit on it .  However, it is rare for someone who is not on a reserved seat to give up their seat to someone more deserving. Elevators at the train stations are used in the order of those who came to the elevator to queue up first, even if there is someone more deserving at the end of the queue. Of course, this is not always the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singapore’s messiah, the government, does, of course, step in to solve the problem. In government grocery stores, seniors can skip the queue when paying for food. More reserved seats are being created in trains to match Singapore’s rapidly ageing population. Signs are put up in public places to remind people to be courteous to each other. However, is this form of contrived courtesy really the best measure in the long run? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courtesy needs to come from within. If we continue to manufacture courtesy in Singapore, I think we will forget as a people it’s not of those things that we are instructed to do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I was in a good mood today, heading to terminal 4 (Changi Airport Singapore) for a short vacation in Bali. The shuttle bus from terminal 3 was packed with equally excited travellers, most of which seemed to be Singaporean based on their looks and accents.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Traveler&amp;#8217;s Worst Nightmare</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Traveler's-Worst-NIghtmare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Traveler's Worst Nightmare" /><published>2018-07-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Traveler's-Worst-NIghtmare</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Traveler's-Worst-NIghtmare/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-have-neither-showered-nor-slept-in-the-comfort-of-a-bed-or-really-any-comfortable-surface-in-3-days-i-would-be-lying-if-i-said-i-am-able-to-type-this-article-without-spell-checker-and-auto-correct-doing-some-very-heavy-lifting-im-tired-hungry-and-hallucinating-plus-i-can-smell-myself&quot;&gt;I have neither showered nor slept in the comfort of a bed (or really, any comfortable surface) in 3 days. I would be lying if I said I am able to type this article without spell-checker and auto-correct doing some very heavy lifting. I’m tired, hungry, and hallucinating. Plus, I can smell myself.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the past 48 hours, my friend and I have experienced 2 of probably the worst possible things that can happen to a tourist - getting our belongings stolen, and getting a flight canceled without being re-booked.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nightmare began on the 27th of July in the evening in Brussels, Belgium. Having spent the previous night at the Athens airport to save some dough, my friend and I were already pretty tired. We had wrapped up a pretty awesome day walking around Brussels, and had especially enjoyed an insightful tour at the European Parliament in Brussels. Having had a nice, heavy dinner in Pizza Hut, we wanted to get a couple of Belgian beers and sit in the city centre, and just chill for a bit. That night was going to become another night at the airport, and our flight was the following morning at 6.30am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to play Heads-up to kill some time (and decide who would get the next round) after finding a park bench to sit on. Our bags were between us on the bench, and my pal Shubz left his DSLR camera on the other side of his body, well within arms’ length. While playing the game, we saw someone come and sit beside him, and he left after a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of rounds in, Shubz said that he wanted to check on our belongings, and that’s when we realized it - the camera was gone. We think the man who sat beside us was of African descent because of his skin tone. Thousands of dollars of equipment gone, but infinitesimal compared to what was inside the camera - almost all our pictures from the past month of this trip. Hundreds of hours spent in the hot sun by Shubz over the past month, all gone just like that. For me, taking pictures whilst traveling has always been to serve as a physical take-away, but to Shubz, photography was the end-goal of this month in Europe. I travel to see new places and broaden my horizon, and sometimes take pictures to share with others. Shubz, however, travels to take photos. He plans his entire day around where he needs to be at what time in the day to take that perfect shot. He climbs fences into private properties, jumps over barricades, and camps in the hot sun with hundreds of like-minded tourists around him, all for that perfect shot. He wakes up early in the morning to catch sunrises, and often goes to spots late at night to take night shots. All that effort, all gone, just like that. In broad daylight, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shubz, if you’re reading this, I have no words to express how terrible I feel, but I know that I don’t know the half of it. I know it could have well been me instead of you having had something stolen. I also hope that you this incident does not scare you in any way with regards to traveling, or diminishes that crazy passion for photography in your soul. It’s an inspiration to me, and I’m sure to many others. Keep at it buddy, and I’m sorry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To top it off, the Belgian police were absolutely useless. I tried to coerce them to follow me to the site so that they could see for themselves the site of the crime, but they instead told me to head back there myself and call the police hotline if we see the suspect. Because he’ll obviously be in the area after stealing the camera, right? They titled the police report as “Black camera strap stolen” and refuse to add the model number or camera serial number to the report. I think they think that we were wasting their time reporting this crime, and clearly were not taking us seriously. When we went to check on the status of the investigations the next day, the policemen stared at us &lt;em&gt;as if it was their job to investigate crime and help people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We grudgingly made our to the airport after that, reaching around 11pm for a 6.30am flight. We barely spoke to each other, me because I didn’t know what to say to make Shubz feel better, and Shubz because the most important thing in his life was taken away from him hours ago, with perhaps nothing to grasp onto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found a quiet spot in the airport to lie down, and did so hugging our bags. We &lt;strong&gt;did not&lt;/strong&gt; want any more drama. We just wanted to reach Copenhagen with everything we had with us, and wanted to shower and sleep after 2 days of not being able to do so. &lt;strong&gt;Was that too much to ask?&lt;/strong&gt; At 6am, after some uncomfortable hours of awkward rest on a cold floor, we saw that our Ryanair flight was canceled. We were given no information on why it was canceled, but &lt;em&gt;thankfully, someone from Ryanair gave us pieces of paper that said our flight was canceled, and that we should just rebook ourselves online, without bothering them. And their website was down.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After standing in a line for about an hour with other angry passengers, we were told that the earliest flight to Copenhagen we could be put on was on Wednesday, 4 days later. I was supposed to be in Singapore by then, let alone Copenhagen, or my final stop, Stockholm. We knew Ryanair had a reputation, and chose to just get a refund, all 20 Euros of it each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent the next few hours trying to find alternative ways to reach Copenhagen. After all, we had already paid for 2 nights in a very expensive hostel in Copenhagen, and then a train from there to Stockholm. Trying to get ourselves a flight on the same day was one of the most stressful situations I’d ever been in. Fares were going up, literally every minute. We eventually settled on a 300-Euro flight to Copenhagen via Frankfurt - a 15 hour journey in total. Ours initially was less than 2 hours, and 15 times cheaper. Well, what choice did we have, right? And nothing else, could go wrong, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wrong.&lt;/strong&gt; We found out around noon, seven hours before our replacement flight, that our flight tickets were canceled because of bank authorization issues (or so kiwi.com claims) and we were going to be given a refund. Yay, another refund. And now we had less than half the time to make another booking, and flights were on average, about 1000 Euros to Copenhagen. Clearly, the benevolent, all-knowing being was having his/her/their fun with us. We eventually booked a flight directly to Stockholm, skipping Copenhagen together, at 20 times the original cost of the ticket to Copenhagen. We also wasted two nights of hostel stays, train tickets, and the opportunity to explore Copenhagen, something I was really looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I type this, I’m sitting in an airport in Warsaw, Poland. When checking in at Belgium, we were told by staff the system said our final stop was not Stockholm but Berlin or something, I can’t even remember. I didn’t know if to laugh, cry, scream, or just wish that I combusted into carbon. Fortunately, it was a mistake. I have 10 hours to kill before my next flight. I have neither the will, nor the energy, nor the money to leave the airport. All I’m doing is praying for no more surprises. I’ve been told that this is the &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; of traveling. Please pray my check-in bags make it to Stockholm at the same time as me as well, I really need to shower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Friends, always make sure to watch out for your belongings when traveling. In Singapore, we take this for granted. Over my month in Europe, we heard of many cases of people’s belongings being stolen from the bags on their bodies, from the airport while they were sleeping next to it, or in front of their eyes. Someone in Belgium next to me at the police station even had their car stolen, with all their belongings, passport, documents, everything inside of it. Also, while flight delays and cancellations cannot be prevented, it makes sense to know your rights as a passenger when they do, and have purchased travel insurance to share some of the blow when shit hits the fan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I have neither showered nor slept in the comfort of a bed (or really, any comfortable surface) in 3 days. I would be lying if I said I am able to type this article without spell-checker and auto-correct doing some very heavy lifting. I’m tired, hungry, and hallucinating. Plus, I can smell myself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Venice, Its Not Your Fault</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Venice,-its-Not-Your-Fault/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venice, Its Not Your Fault" /><published>2018-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Venice,-its-Not-Your-Fault</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Venice,-its-Not-Your-Fault/">&lt;p&gt;I don’t have to tell you that Venice is one of the most beautiful places on Earth. What you might not know is that it is suffering with too many tourists, to the point that it’s threatening the city’s very existence. Venice may soon both lose it’s status as a UNESCO world heritage site and enter the “In-Danger List”, normally reserved for ruins in third-world countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A short history&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The independent “Most Scenic Republic of Venice” (yes, that is the actual name) existed from the 8th century to the 18th century. The Doge’s Palace was built in 814, and landmark St Mark’s Basilica in 834. (This Basilica had been burnt down and has been reconstructed.) The celebrated Venetian merchant Marco Polo sailed to China in one of the most fascinating stories of the middle ages in 1271. In 1348, Venice’s population halved because of the plague. Venice enjoyed being one of the largest trading ports in the world in it’s heyday, but declined in 1797 because it could not defend itself, with only 13 ships and a few brigades of mercenaries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incredibly rude waiters, shop-owners, and everyday people led me thinking and researching about why Venetians despise tourists so much. 
This was especially surprising because tourism runs this city, and Venice needs tourists like our bodies need water. A city of about 55,000 locals, Venice sees up to 300,000 tourists in a weekend alone. Venetians have raised issues that range from vandalism and destruction of historical sites, unaffordable housing, bathing (sometimes completely naked) in historical fountains of cultural and religious significance, and crowding on public bridges and transport that lead to a severe degradation of their lives. One can view posters that say “Tourists go away” in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city has been fighting hard to combat the woes of over-tourism, and keep locals staying in the city. If the population of Venice drops below 40,000, it will be unsustainable as a city. The city already has a Venetians-first policy, and presenting a ‘Venezia Unica Oro’, or gold card, gets you priority boarding on boats (this is a huge perk because boats tend to be extremely crowded). Boats cost 6 times more for tourists on a single-ticket, and are 50 Euros for 3 days for tourists and 50 Euros for 5 years for locals. The city also practices tourist pricing, where virtually everything is priced (read: overpriced) for tourists. Proving you’re local will get you a much cheaper bottle of coke, meal, or any form of service at the same establishment. Entry fees for monuments, museums, and other attractions, which can range from 5 - 30 Euros, also only apply to tourists. It is clear that Venetians come first in Venice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the city has launched a #EnjoyRespectVenice campaign, which provides instructions on how to behave here as a tourist. Instructions to be followed include not sitting down in public spaces for meals or to picnic, not crossing a bridge without purpose (taking photos is not an acceptable purpose), and not standing on the street without motivation. Having bought some take-away pasta at a stall in Venice, we were given strict instructions after being served on where we were allowed to &lt;em&gt;stand&lt;/em&gt; and eat. Sitting was out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One major problem that Venice faces is a large number of cruise ships that dock here and send tourists to visit for the day. These tourists do not stay overnight and hence do that support hotels. Cruises also have meals included, so they have no motivation to eat here ias well. In 2016, protesters used boats to form a line and prevent cruise ships from entering the lagoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly what has been done to save Venice from too many tourists is not enough, and there are many ideas being floated to help the situation. This includes charging tourists a daily fee for being in Venice, much like Disneyland. A fee in the range of 100 Euros or so is likely to start to curb the number of tourists that enter Venice. Mayors in the past have also requested for the power to close off the city on days with too many tourists. However, because Venice is completely dependent on tourism for its survival, closing off the city for a prolonged period is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the solution is, Venetians better think hard and fast, the city is sinking 2mm a year - and will possibly be underwater a century from now. It’s not her fault she’s so beautiful - and I have pictures to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/venice06.JPG&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/venice07.JPG&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/venice08.JPG&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/venice09.JPG&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I don’t have to tell you that Venice is one of the most beautiful places on Earth. What you might not know is that it is suffering with too many tourists, to the point that it’s threatening the city’s very existence. Venice may soon both lose it’s status as a UNESCO world heritage site and enter the “In-Danger List”, normally reserved for ruins in third-world countries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Europe In 10 Pictures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Europe-in-10-Pictures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Europe In 10 Pictures" /><published>2018-07-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Europe-in-10-Pictures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Europe-in-10-Pictures/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;im-no-photographer-but-a-picture-speaks-a-thousand-words-here-are-some-no-nonsense-pictures-i-took-with-my-iphone-around-france-spain-and-italy-complete-with-some-context&quot;&gt;I’m no photographer, but a picture speaks a thousand words. Here are some no-nonsense pictures I took with my iPhone around France, Spain and Italy, complete with some context.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/bridgeOfSighs.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bridge of Sighs is an infamous arch bridge that connects the Doge’s Palace to its prisons. It is named as such because condemned prisoners had their last view of Venice (and freedom) from this bridge before they met their executioners. Sigh indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alhambra.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the patio of the Palace of Charles V. It was taken at the Alhambra in Granada, Spain. Alhambra literally means “Red One” in Arabic, and was built in the time when Spain was rules by Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lyonBasilica.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Basilica of Notre-Dame de Fourvière is a minor basilica in Lyon. It is dedicated to Virgin Mary who is believed to have saved the city from the Black Death, which killed 30-60% of Europe’s population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sagrada.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still unfinished 136 years later, the Sagrada Familia is a Roman Catholic church designed by Antonio Gaudi. He died in 1926, when less than a quarter of the project was finished, after being run over by a tram. A sad way to die for someone who saw the church as the work of his lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/eiffel.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eiffel Tower, an 81-storey tower built in 1889, was supposed to be a temporary structure. Many artists and engineers protested the design of the tower, and never wanted it built. It is now the most visited paid monument in the world, with 7 million visitors in 2015. Way to answer to haters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/burano.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brightly coloured houses of Burano, now a major attraction for tourists to Venice, were painted for a more practical purpose in the past - to be more visible to fishermen in a fog. Today, strict regulations govern what colours each house can be painted as, and no adjacent houses can be painted in the same colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/murano.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No two pieces of work are the same from the glass factories of world-famous Murano. Murano’s Glass Masters have a minimum of 15-20 years of experience. Everything is learnt through apprenticeship - no student loans necessary, and the exact composition of raw materials used to make the beautiful glass items is a secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/tarifa.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southern-most point in Europe and only 12 km away from Morocco in Africa, Tarifa is a beautiful beach town that is a hidden gem. On clear, calm days, you possibly can see whales and dolphins from the coast. Here we can see a humpback breaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alcazar.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real Alcazar de Sevilla is a palace built for the Chrisrtian King Peter of Castile from the ruins of a Muslim residential fortress. You may recognize it as The Water Gardens of Dorne from the Game of Thrones. Possibly a spoiler?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lyonCroix.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le Mer de Canuts in Croix-Rousse, Lyon is a huge mural on the side of a residential building. It is said to be Europe’s largest fresco. Dating back to 1986, it has now been updated to reflect the changes in the neighbourhood since.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I’m no photographer, but a picture speaks a thousand words. Here are some no-nonsense pictures I took with my iPhone around France, Spain and Italy, complete with some context.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Warming Up With London And Stockholm</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Warming-Up-With-London-and-Stockholm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warming Up With London And Stockholm" /><published>2018-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Warming-Up-With-London-and-Stockholm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Warming-Up-With-London-and-Stockholm/">&lt;p&gt;It was in March this year that I decided to spend much of my summer break 2018 backpacking through Europe. Having a friend who was already interning in Stockholm for the past one year made it a whole lot easier to make the leap. In this and the next few posts, I will share stories, tips, and experiences that &lt;em&gt;hopefully&lt;/em&gt; will transcend a mere transcription of my travels. My aim is to share my experiences, hopefully in a way that is useful to you, the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off my journey flying directly from Singapore to London via Norwegian Air. This flight is supposed to the longest budget flight in the world, and I did not know what to expect - however, I do have to say that I have absolutely no complaints for the price I paid (around 500 SGD from Singapore to London, and then London to Stockholm inclusive). Meals were served on time and the plane was brand new. One small tip may be to bring your own 3.5mm jack headphones if you wish to enjoy the in-flight entertainment. Norwegian Air also lands at Gatwick Airport instead of Heathrow for most premium airlines, but they are both pretty much equidistant from the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived in London after about 15 hours and &lt;strong&gt;obviously&lt;/strong&gt; bought a 20GB data sim from Vodafone, which works freely in the entire “Europe Zone” for about 25 pounds. The train from Gatwick Airport to the city cost about 14 pounds, which is probably the cheapest way to get to London if you don’t have a friend to pick you up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London is one of the largest, most densely populated, and culturally rich places in the world, and often the first pit stop for backpackers heading deeper into Europe. People have been coming to London for the museums, pubs, theatre, royalty, and history for generations, and it’s easy to see why. In my short few days (and my second time in London), I did most of the high-key touristy things, and enjoyed all of it almost equally. I’m personally not a big fan of royalty because I don’t believe in celebrating the luckiest sperm over generations, so Buckingham Palace wasn’t in my list for sure - I did however walk past the palace. My main motivation being in London was actually to spend time with my childhood friend Daksh, and it was great seeing him and spending his after-work hours with me. His mum was around and she made some amazing food for us, and World Cup Seasons meant exciting evenings. World Cup season would last deep through my journey, and the finals would be whilst I was in Spain - this surely made me wish they were in the finals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/londonEye.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time in Stockholm was pretty eye-opening though. It was my first time in Scandinavia and although I was warned about how expensive it was going to be, it was still shocking anyways. I paid about 15 bucks for fast food for lunch, and it was the only meal I had outside. Public transport is decent although expensive, and that is how one would go around the city - cabs are very expensive. The main highlight in Stockholm is supposed to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vasamuseet.se/en&quot;&gt;Vasa Museum&lt;/a&gt;, which is basically a large building with an almost perfectly-restored viking ship (The Vasa). The ship sank in the 17th century because of human arrogance (King Gustav wanted a grand ship better than the Danish’s), human stupidity (the two different sides of the ship were built by two different groups of builders who used the length of their hands for measurement, and they had different hand sizes because they were of different races) and engineering mistakes (the ship was designed too tall and too heavy to float effectively). Before visiting Vasa Museum, you should know that the entire museum is about this salvaged ship, and at around 30 dollars, I personally didn’t find it quite worth the money. The ship would have barely been a single exhibit in any other museum, but it was the entirety of the Vasa Museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swedenBoats.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also visited Skansen, which is an open-air zoo and museum. It was a pretty interesting experience and cost around the same as the Vasa, but had a lot more things to do. While some things were paid inside Skansen after paying the basic entry free, most were free. It is a giant space, and one could easily spend an entire day walking around the park. The zoo had a decent variety of animals (decent because it is hard to compete with the Singapore Zoo, frequently lauded as world’s best, and other zoos overseas that have five horses and call themselves a zoo). Skansen’s zoo was in between. They had animals like wolves, bears, otters, lions, and bison. My short 2 days in Stockholm were interesting because although I didn’t do much, I did get to learn about how the Swedes live - they are family oriented - I hear they have like 6 weeks of normal leave a year, have &lt;strong&gt;two years&lt;/strong&gt; of childcare leave that they can use before the child is five, not including weekends - making it about two and a half years effectively. They believe in gender equality, and most companies strive to ensure an equal distribution of men and women in the workforce. Most people wrap up work around 4pm, after which they pick a picnic spot to hang out with their family. The Swedes take their family time very seriously for sure. Studies are very heavily subsidized in Sweden, and many have Masters and PHDs. Degrees don’t feature class honours, and everyone in society is equally respected. A very different system from what we have in Singapore, with more emphasis on work life, grades, and status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am super excited for my journey to the rest of Europe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swedenMe.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100000000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">It was in March this year that I decided to spend much of my summer break 2018 backpacking through Europe. Having a friend who was already interning in Stockholm for the past one year made it a whole lot easier to make the leap. In this and the next few posts, I will share stories, tips, and experiences that hopefully will transcend a mere transcription of my travels. My aim is to share my experiences, hopefully in a way that is useful to you, the reader.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Bae Area</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Bae-Area/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bae Area" /><published>2018-06-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Bae-Area</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/The-Bae-Area/">&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to spend 2017 living and working in the San Francisco Bay Area, California, and it was definitely one of the greatest personal and professional experiences of my life. Being in the Bay Area was refreshing - you surely learn a great deal about yourself when you’re outside of your comfort zone (10,000 miles to be precise) - but it would be injustice to call it outside my comfort zone really. Over the year, I learnt to not only be comfortable where I was, but also grew a newfound appreciation for what it meant to be liberal, American, and be perhaps, truly free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bay Area hosted some of the kindest people I met - I was blessed with colleagues who treated interns with as much respect, if not more, as they treated fellow colleagues - horror stories from university friends had me expecting much worse. Throughout the year, I always felt like all my ideas, however naive, were valued just as much as the directors’. Having barely covered the essential computer science classes to be able to contribute at a decent level to any company, let alone production code being used by over a million users, I definitely was at the tip of my toes when I first joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getepic.com&quot;&gt;Epic!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I was in great hands to say the least - colleagues and more experienced engineers took a great deal of time off from their schedules daily to teach me the ways of the programmer - it was clear that they absolutely loved what they did, and also saw it as a humble duty to ensure they would pass on some of their learnings and knowledge to me. Their passion was extremely motivational and inspiring. Things were initially a little difficult for me at Epic! - I had a million questions all the time and I did not want to bug the other engineers all the time, and it meant that I sometimes spent hours staring at the screen trying to figure things out myself - and this would have taken someone with experience minutes. As a young intern in his first internship, you don’t know what you don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, engineering to me has also always been about the struggle (mentally, sometimes emotionally, rarely physically when I want to destroy everything with a wire coming out of it), the science (and art) of programming is one that that surely requires you to go through the pains of coming up with a solution yourself - giving it a Google (or a Hey Max, how’d you do this?) too soon is akin to depriving yourself with the joy (read: pain) of coming up with a solution yourself. What made it even more confusing was understanding where to draw the line: how much of the other engineers’ time was I deserving of, where should I give up and approach them, and at what point should I give up staring for my screen and actually approach someone for help? It really was very confusing for me at the beginning. It took me a great deal of time to understand that - and I promise you I never took this privilege lightly - that my job as an intern was to learn. I was there to prioritise my own learning from the best, and adding any value to the company was a side-effect of my stint at the company. I will forever be grateful to everyone at Epic! For investing in me, teaching me what it means to have a supportive work environment, and teaching me the joy in programming. I hope I can do the same for someone else one day too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no one wants to be a dud for a full year, but it took me a while to realise that the best way for me to give back to the company (which really was a great priority to me) was to be the best engineer that I could be. The best way to do that was to invest in myself but asking lots of questions, spending time at work reading up on concepts and technologies I was unfamiliar with, and learning by making mistakes. I realised that in the second of my year-long internship, when I started to ask more questions and prioritise my learning more, I actually was able to empower myself to write better code for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having come from conservative Singapore, a great culture shock for me was how open Americans were : it was completely fine to talk about a late night out or have a cold one at the work place (beer-o-clock, we called it). This, I realised, actually worked in favour of the company - happy employees = productive workplace. This initially took me a while to get used to, but was definitely a refreshing (and I would daresay, superior) experience compared to the traditional, conservative workplace. The company structure was mostly flat too, and it went a long way in making everyone feel like they were important, and wanting to do their best. Micro-management makes great slaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most heartwarming things that I realised being in California was that everyone I spoke to was truly passionate about what they did. You could tell that they looked forward to being at work every morning, and didn’t mind staying until they finished their self-appointed tasks of the day. Here in Asia, people are generally more conservative with their career options - You could be a doctor, lawyer, engineer, or a loser. However, in America, a surprising number of people actually follow their dreams. They study what they want in college, and are not afraid to make switches mid-career if they feel like they do not enjoy what they do. I was amazed to find out that most of the engineers in the team did not have degrees in engineering - they varied from majors in music, sociology, audio-engineering, to even biology! This was by no means a coincidence though, Americans are willing to give people without the right paper credentials a chance, and in return, are paid back by passionate employees. I hope that we can do the same in Singapore with time to come, and focus less on the paper chase. Innovation can only be kindled if people enjoy what they do. Creativity is a by-product of passion and an open mind, and not quite academic rigour. Perhaps following your dreams is perhaps the sure-st way of being happy, and sometimes risking it all to do so is a holy obligation. Many colleagues who had done just that were reaping the benefits of doing so. Being happy was a choice they consciously made, albeit through trial and error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in California had other great advantages too - Redwood City’s (where I worked) claim to fame was Climate Best by Government Test. And I couldn’t agree more - temperature was practically between 8 degrees celcius and 20 degrees celcius all year long - days were generally long with sunny afternoons. The weather was supportive to sport and travelling practically all year long. California is also home to a great deal of microclimates - within the state, you have beaches, mountains, valleys, desserts, and even a rainforest. Redwood trees, some of the tallest trees in the world, are plentiful in the Bay. You do not have to travel far to see snow or sand, and some of the most beautiful places in the world, like Yosemite, Lake Tahoe, and King’s Canyon National Park are just hours away by car from the Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My year in California was nothing short of amazing - I’m fortunate to have been able to spend half of my Sophomore year and half of my Junior year abroad interning full-time and taking a couple of classes under the guidance of Stanford and Berkeley Professors. I will surely be back!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">I had the opportunity to spend 2017 living and working in the San Francisco Bay Area, California, and it was definitely one of the greatest personal and professional experiences of my life. Being in the Bay Area was refreshing - you surely learn a great deal about yourself when you’re outside of your comfort zone (10,000 miles to be precise) - but it would be injustice to call it outside my comfort zone really. Over the year, I learnt to not only be comfortable where I was, but also grew a newfound appreciation for what it meant to be liberal, American, and be perhaps, truly free.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello, World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writings/Hello,-World/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello, World" /><published>2018-05-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writings/Hello,-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writings/Hello,-World/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lying on the bed at 4am watching Netflix made me realise: I’m a bum and all I do is &lt;em&gt;consume&lt;/em&gt; content. I thought it’d be great for me to &lt;em&gt;produce&lt;/em&gt; content once in a while too. I hope to use this space on the web to share content that I have created - writings, commentaries, maybe a few drawings here and there. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Gadodia</name><email>me@harshgadodia.com</email></author><summary type="html">Motivation</summary></entry></feed>